welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where equal hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
and thank you Peter for having having me
on
yeah I think we did meet over over
Twitter exchanges and then also maybe
some Facebook bits as well but I was uh
you know me and many other people in the
rally point alpha ap crowd were big fans
of your your write up a while ago now I
guess this point about the culture wars
and that's a topic that's near and dear
to my heart although certain things have
now pressed themselves to higher plane
of urgency but but the the thing I
wanted to talk about today and actually
let me just check real quick how much
time should I take for this initial bit
of exposition perhaps I recommend like
anywhere from ten to twenty five minutes
oh okay that's that's quite a bit okay
let's see how far I get in doing these
chunks I don't want people to get too
bored but I'll start with let's do let's
do a part one part two
okay so part one is about choice
consequence of meaning and part two will
be about Moloch and the system of the
world and what this moment teaches us
about about that okay so so part one I
think the the best way to put it is is
that you know I'll just a little
background my contention is that here in
the West we have a theory of
individualism and we have a philosophy
of individual rights kind of all of the
sort of ground playing philosophy for
our society and for our politics and our
personal philosophies they're really
grounded this idea that we are free
we're individuals we are free we have
freedom and if you really think about it
for the most part we don't go too far
nasty well what what is freedom really
we just sort of say why I've choice and
therefore I'm free I mean I think most
people would find that to be a fairly
not an unreasonable position to take
right I can decide whatever I want to be
I'll give you a firefighter I give you
an astronaut I can go and just sit in a
hut all day long I have choices and
therefore I'm free and so this first
part is really looking into what is a
choice most importantly what is
consequential choice and how that ties
into actual meaning in life so the when
we look at kind of generally kind of
modernity in the West here
we realize that of course I'm free but I
mean I live within institutions I live
in a big city I live even if I live out
in the countryside I am very aware I'm
part of political structures and legal
structures I'm somewhat bounded I'm
really can't say I'm completely free
obviously but if you really start
thinking about it more and more you look
at what is it that people do in their
daily lives well for the most part
people are pretty boring they have a
very set routine you could be a farmer
out on 25 acres you could be a city you
know some some person with a job in the
city
but people have routines and those
routines are actually quite fixed and
even given that they could do something
different than the given day they don't
do that so so this idea that we have
choice and so that we're we're free well
if that's the case most of us are not
manifesting that freedom in any
meaningful way so when we look at these
large structured institutions it's not
just they limit our choices it's like
today I could go to someplace I've never
been in the city and do something
completely different but I'm not gonna
write and and the reason I'm not gonna
is because my preferences are shaped and
my life is shaped by more than just hard
constraints of like I can't do this or
that's illegal or there's a thing in my
way so I can't go over there there's a
fence I can't go see that thing it's
it's actually that we are guided
generally so I would say that the the
big thing here the concept here is that
people generally even though they
believe themselves to be free even
though they believe that freedom is
manifest in a large plurality of choices
for the most part that make the same
choice every single day and this is a
critical component that optionality
though the perception of that option
ality is a huge part of the Western
psyche and and I would say that part of
it is because it's so individualistic
it's so says like I don't have to do
anything for you I don't have to you
know you can't make me how many times
you hear kids saying that you can't make
me
right and this same idea it's all
centered around the idea that we make
these choices and my choice is mine and
that's the the center of my agency is
that I can make choices and in fact
it goes a little bit further which is
that you know I have choices and you
have choices so we're gonna be civil to
each other and we can pretend our
choices don't impact each other I can
see movie a you can see movie B I call
it tomato you call it tomato and we can
get on with our lives so that there is a
stability of social civil stability that
emerges from even if you don't manifest
those choices by making different
choices at least the belief that we all
have our individual choices lets us be
civil towards each other
lets us coexist right we can believe it
we are actually not in relationship but
I say this is complete fiction
right and what coronavirus has shown for
us is uh well let's let's put it this
way let's say you're driving down the
road and you're listening let's say it's
beginning of March or late February
sokeep think about that time right there
was they oh this is not no worse than
the flu this is this is a liberal hoax
to to hurt Trump there's any number of
different things right and so you're
driving down the road and maybe you see
Facebook post so you've seen messages
from other people
friends of yours who say oh no this is
really bad there's a pandemic
exponential curves yada yada so you're
driving down the road and you hear on
the radio
some little news segment that says the
first case of Sosa was reported in our
city and now the government is debating
whether or not to go into lockdown or
something else or whatever or do we need
to have masks whatever and so you're
driving down the road and you're at a
stop line you're listening this and now
you have a choice and your choice is do
I turn left and go to the store buy some
hand sanitizer you know just in case
because this thing could be real or do I
go straight and just kind of keep going
home because like whatever this yeah I'm
sure when something is really bad
they'll tell they will tell me and you
know we'll figure it out I guess so so
that's the that's the choice and the
interesting thing about coronavirus is
that at that point in time no one
actually knew right there was sort of
this liminality that was open right then
because if we absolutely if like if
spaceships descended from on high and
said hey everyone this is a global
pandemic y'all should take this
seriously and they blinked out of
existence we would all be aligned and
say okay you know what the liminal
window you know it's snapped we all
believe this is a bad thing let's go do
this thing but but it wasn't that it was
like well is it isn't it is a little
thing is a real thing as a sciences or
whatever so in that window people had to
make a real choice and I call this a
consequential choice because if you
don't take it seriously and you're well
within your rights not to you could go
straight and continue as you've always
done because inaction is still a choice
and you keep going to bars and you don't
like you know here in Austin which is
where I am you know 70 people from
University of Texas so many students
flew down to Florida to you know keep
doing their Florida Party thing and half
of them now have coronavirus right so
they made a choice to just carry on that
choice had a consequence right
you could also decide wait wait maybe I
should take this seriously in just in
case I'm gonna go and just get a little
extra hand sanitizer get a little toilet
paper or whatever it is right I'm not
actually modeling out what this thing
really how how kinda me really plays out
but I'm gonna at least try to like maybe
it's hand sanitizers just I have it with
me just be a little bit safer so you
make a choice even in action even status
quo is a choice and here's the kicker
that choice has a consequence right
because two weeks from now we'll find
out how well you did now can you imagine
like walking down the street if someone
jumps in front of you the gun points at
you and says hey give me all your money
you have a consequential choice there -
right because depending on what you
choose a consequence a very significant
consequence presents itself to you but
with this case of coronavirus there's
this lag right you make the decision and
you're kind of fretting about it and
you're kind of like oh crap oh crap oh
crap and like maybe two weeks later you
find out oh crap I just pass something
on to my you know aging parents or I
just oh my god I think I gave that to my
friend because I went to that party and
then I also went this other party holy
crap right the consequence is in a void
of unavoidable right the the the virus
itself the SARS coronavirus - doesn't
care whether you eat Fox News or watch
CNN or whatever it just it does what it
does so this idea that people now have
to make a choice a real choice and that
there's a consequence that unavoidable
non-narrative narrator bowl away
consequence and then there's a lag super
interesting because that lag forces this
luma this liminal window to be open for
quite some time and and in this context
I want to sort of I want to sort of you
know just highlight that when you are
faced with this you might also have a
little bit of
we're gonna see step above yourself you
say you know what why is this particular
decision harder for me than all the
other decisions in my life because look
at my life I've decided to go on this
trip or I decided to get married or I
decided to you know change jobs or I
decided to move to this town right you
know any number of things have been
decided I make decisions all the time
right and it turns out no you make
choices but really they're expressions
of preference most people in stable it's
a middle-class Western countries it I
would hope maybe for not many people but
but I hope this moment presents them a
bit of self-awareness that this choice
is unlike most of the other choices that
you have been making in your life and in
fact this is a real choice is a real
decision a consequential one most of the
other decisions and choices you make are
basically totally it's like
what color car do you want what color is
your hat well I guess that there's a
whole thing around that but like what
what toppings you want on your pizza
it's not a choice that's not freedom
that's preference and the reason you
want some new freight you know fancy
pizzas because you saw the freaking ad
on TV last week right so the idea here
that that not just a few individuals but
every single person has to make a
consequential choice that's like life
and death consequences and they have to
do it all kind of at the same time and
there's this gap when we find out how
what we did and then the really the
really interesting kickers there's a
social aspect to it too which is I'm the
only one making a consequential you know
making this decision and I decided one
way but all of y'all decide different
way we have a worse outcome but if we
all decide the same way right if we all
decides as a hoax it would carry on with
the economy the economy doesn't crash
bunch of people gonna die maybe more
than the should've but the economy
doesn't crash if we all decide holy crap
this would kill everyone is pandemic we
all walk down the economy crashes but
few people die right and that fewer
person dying could be you it could be a
loved one or a friend right so there's a
prisoner's dilemma aspect to the social
aspect of this thing that's just
absolutely I don't call it perfect but
it's like amazing that we get all of
these different little bits filled in
terms of imposing a consequential social
choice on people and again it puts this
in stark
dressed with what I call the as if
choices that most people kind of
Stumbler through stumble through life
making and believe that it makes them
free because the way that this game is
the way you know I'm one of the people
kind of the game baked game be movement
if you will most of things I say I am
right I guess it's one of those
movements and so the game a world has
been really really good at giving people
a stringing them along with a small a
series of small as if choices that are
really just preferences but that have no
downside consequences in fact we've end
a lot of things to people to insulate
them from the consequences of bad
decisions so ultimately these little
decisions kind of ratchet them into
almost like a lobster trap or something
else it kind of funnels them into a part
of the face space where ultimately
they're screwed like their long-term
optionality is strategic optionality is
compressed but it feels like real
choices all the way along the way and
that's that's the game that's the trick
that's the lobster trap right so like
you know do I take a little of extra
credit you know I get another extra
$5,000 if I can take this credit card
right or do I get this upgrade on this
car I mean it's just at the edge of what
I came into the dealership with my
budget but I can you know what I do this
extend the payments out a little bit
all these little decisions right they're
there to give people in a moment a way
to buy some risk hedging but what
they're trading away is large
optionality and that does little as of
choices those little preference things
kind of glide people into that and
that's that's really where the majority
of people are quite stuck mechanist Rao
has a wonderful thing called the Gervase
theory and he holds it in contrast like
the Peter Principle or the Gilbert
principle and the Gervase theory was his
structure of what corporate America are
really corporate structures look like
you have sociopaths at the top and you
have losers at the bottom who know they
will never reach the top they're just
phoning it in they're doing the minimum
thing possible to get a wage they're
playing the game just as the games
trying to play them the people at the
top are leading they're making
consequential choices they're really
looking out for themselves most the time
but they they know they're there you
know both of these are liminal and they
both have made their choices how they're
gonna play the game and in the middle is
a tier of clueless people who facilitate
the dream for the people down here the
people in the middle they could ever
become at the top and they also to help
soften the blow of the bad decisions of
the people the top so this clueless here
in the middle are the ones who exist in
a state of non liminality and I would
say that the vast majority of middle
class Westerners who let's say they do
all the things right take out a mortgage
they listen to the news they try to get
their kids to have good grades to go to
school they try to figure how to save up
in this college education saving fund to
pay for super expensive colleges just
getting more more expensive they do all
these things because those we're
supposed to do but they don't ever
really ask why should college be ten
times more expensive now than just when
I went to school they don't ask all
these different kinds of things right
they don't ask how does the money
actually get made what are the two
trillion dollars come from I thought we
couldn't come up with 300 million for
this other thing that I like right so
they don't actually understand how the
system works they're there just to
continue the fiction of the American
Dream mode sake and I'm American so the
lavas will contextualize in the culture
of America but but this idea that people
have a real choice when it comes to
coronavirus everyone's got to make the
same choices consequential highly
consequential this might actually get
people to realize oh you know what
compared to this set of things like do I
participate in the destruction of the
American economy or the Western economy
like do I just do I contributed this and
intentionally and explicitly that's a
real choice I get to make and if I have
to make that decision in that choice
that choice feels totally unlike a lot
of these other choices I've made right
and and I'm hoping that it gets people
to snap out of that reverie of the
clueless middle and realize you know
what I'm I'm smoking crack I haven't I
mean do I really have a shot at getting
beyond middle manager and making it into
this league over here do I really have a
shot at making out of the middle class
if I do all these things that they tell
me I'm supposed to do is my kid really
gonna get into Harvard
you know I hope it snaps people out of
the as if decision making as if choices
and and hopefully maybe out of this idea
of as if freedom right cuz real freedom
is not about just picking sausage or
pepperoni on your pizza real freedom is
not about a bunch of choices
real freedom is having the optionality
having the ability the agency and the
Trinity to live a meaningful life and so
the other piece of this tied to this and
I'll end phase one with this thought one
of the you know John's Reiki talks about
the meaning crisis I think that people
making a lot of azov choices is sort of
like um you know when you when they when
they had loved the microbeads in like in
in all the hair products and stuff that
the exfoliating like little micro
plastics that were going out and like
filling fish bellies when they cut open
the fish you see the inside of the fish
is filled with this crap right the fish
thought it was food it wasn't really
food it was killing them I was out of
nourishment they starve to death even
they're constantly eating I think that's
a perfect perfect metaphor for the kinds
of as if choices that crowd people's
lives the as if decisions they have to
make there's really not that many
decision people really need to make
because the big decisions are the ones
with consequence so if a decision or a
choice doesn't change here in long term
consequence doesn't matter it's not
really a choice just go with whatever
right so I think this the key thing here
is that because people have been just
baking making preference
choices and not real consequential
choices there's a lack of meaning
because there's a lack of endowment
effect you know that whether you pick
pepperoni or not whether you drink the
Bud Light or not you're still not gonna
get all the hot chicks in the beer
commercial right you know you can you
can go buy the cool car it's not gonna
put you into the expensive part
neighborhood of town right all of these
kinds of things ultimately create that
meaning crisis because meaning comes
from people being able to make
consequential choices owning those
choices and seeing them through to their
consequence and then and then actually
cranking that loop and saying I actually
have a part in the trajectory of my life
so ok I'll wrap up phase one or part one
with that thoughts feedback Peter yeah
do you want to jump into some Q&A there
do ya let's go ahead and let's take a
couple questions and see so we got here
sure so if anyone has any questions you
can write in the chat box I have some
questions right now which i'll warm
peter up with again if you want me to
read to just to indicate that and the
chat so yeah I really liked all that and
then the phrase that came to mind I
think it'd be good to run with it is
that this whole thing is an opportunity
for freedom and so do you like that that
specific phrase do you think that's
going to be encouraging for people to
think that way um I think I think that
might be a narrative bridge too far
right now but I would say it's an
opportunity for meaning it's an
opportunity to to like I maybe encourage
people to be a little bit more
intentional in in self-aware and
reflecting on why they're doing the
things they're doing right right because
this is a consequential choice this is
not just choosing which color you want
in your car this is actually something
quite important how are you getting to
that decision and as they walk through
it and as they as they walk that pattern
of actual explicit intentional decision
making they're gonna realize oh I you
know why don't I have to do this more
often well maybe they won't realize but
we should encourage them to think about
why don't you do this more often
why do you not have the skills to do an
explicit sense making loop around
something like this is it either a your
life is so privileged and comfortable
that you don't have to or is it be that
you've been you're basically a chicken
and a feedlot you know you don't have to
and that's bad it's not safe right right
and how are you personally in this
consequential we're gonna call it the
consequential legs and the consequential
gap how are you personally like
operating in this state um well I would
give myself about a c-minus because I
have a full-time job better runner this
is a company and I got a steer that
thing through various things I mean
maybe not maybe not see - there I should
give myself a little more you know we
have to learn to forgive ourselves it's
one of the things that we have to do
here right is treating the whole body
treating the whole mind training all
these things in our egos as well so
maybe I'm not doing C - but I don't
think I'm doing I don't think I'm even
doing any - I think I could do a lot
better the way I'm trying to track it is
I do try to spend some part of my day
understand the broader scope what's
going on and I spend some part of my day
talking to people and just asking
questions like how are you thinking
about this here's what I've got I'm very
open about what I don't know and I asked
I try to get input from people and even
within the company you know trying to
trying to think about how do we model
what the economy's going to look like
you know there's gonna be complete
disaster is it gonna we start are gonna
go to war with China and then we have a
wartime economy and we should go try to
get some of those sweet defense
contracts like what is the thing that I
do to take care of the people I'm
responsible for right so there's just
for me it's just asking more questions
more intently and more explicitly
reaching out and looking for what I
would call the gosh had a cute term for
this a year ago but I forgot it now but
it's it's this it's almost like creating
a negative capacity in your mind
basically carving out a way to say no
you're full of and just have that
person on your left shoulder all the
time right constantly saying here's the
thing you don't like and you hate it but
what if it was right and now I generally
run with that anyway like generally that
person is always there but in this case
I have to more intentionally explicitly
manifest that that person or that that
cognitive center because I don't think I
mean I we're in this liminal zone
I think the mainstream narratives about
this virus are I think the
mainstream narratives about what the
consequences might be are
because what I realize is that if even
any of these are partially true the
consequence must be that there is
state-level massive diplomacy things
happening right now to avoid World War 3
and if those things collapsed and I do
not trust leadership in the structure of
leadership we have the top of the
American government certainly and I
certainly do not trust the leadership of
the Chinese government because in this
game it's a it's a game of Thrones it's
a game of states if the Chinese the
Russians have a chance to gang up and
completely cripple America they
absolutely will instantly they will and
you know we've done such a great job as
American leadership in galvanizing NATO
and all of our classic allies right in
the last three years that we're gonna
have I'm sure we have a super coherent
response to that kind of so like
that's kind of stuff I try to reason
about but then I try to you know I'm
just trying to run multiple loops at
multiple different levels none of it
makes you feel particularly good
especially as a Chinese person here in I
mean an actual person from Wuhan
originally I was born there
here in America where obviously you know
racist sentiments have been stoked for
political purposes for last 20 years so
no it's not it's not great but I'm just
trying to hold open the possibility
spaces so I'm looking at everything
about how unpleasant it is right right
so we have some questions popping up in
the chat area would you like to read
your question to Peter sure I would love
to hi Peter thanks sorry
my question and maybe the wording is not
as clean as I'd like it to be but do you
feel like this situation with Koba it
will raise awareness for slash do you
think that we're even capable of making
intentional consequences consequential
choices where our consequences aren't
seen through for like another 10 or so
years so something like climate change
where the work where the choices that
were making now you know we won't really
see the consequences for years and years
to come
whereas like we're struggling to make
choices where we won't see the
consequences for another two weeks
right right very good question I think
there's I hope well it's it's the the
journey of a thousand miles starts with
a first step right and if in this
process we restore a little bit more
credibility for mathematical modeling
for data-driven decision if we put a
little bit more rigor into how science
and the public sector our intellectual
like public intellectuals or whatever
how these scientists hold journalists
accountable for crafting mainstream
narratives because I think that that
does all these different things we have
institutional break down in these styles
levels that's what we can't make do
sense making decisioning on these long
time frames and I'm hoping that
currently what it does is sort of like
like when a train locomotive backs up
and then pulls forward right I think
right now it's a backing up moment so we
get a little bit at least get a couple
of the first rail cars hooked up to the
locomotive of actually having you know
data-driven explicit intentional science
and modeling around long term
consequences and broad consequences and
and I'll cite two things one is I'm
conversation with Tristan Harris and and
he was just pointing out that you know
the it's we shouldn't give ourselves too
much well maybe who's quite saying this
but saying we should expect it should be
natural that people have trouble with
this kind of thing because our primary
brain stem in our emotional centers and
all these things that whole the sense
making loop of human brain fits inside
of human brain right and it's it nature
usually doesn't over-engineer so is
designed to make consequential decisions
roaming the African savannah right is
this thing gonna kill me is this thing
coming at me really fast does it look
like the sharp teeth I'm gonna go
run right there's like these kinds of
consequential decisions you don't have
to sit there and say yeah you know I
drew some stuff on a cave wall and I'm
gonna give it two weeks I'm gonna see
what happens like you don't run doodle
hoops like that right you basically you
know you should you throw pointy things
that things to eat them or things with
pointing these come at you and you run
and that's your general like that's the
OODA loop that's the the frequency or
the timeframe the characteristic
wavelength of time that you have to
solve for so the fact that we are able
to build collectives to integrate over a
broader period of time over a more
complex set of phenomenon is amazing in
it of its own self to try to do this
over ten years that's a big that's a
bigger leap and and you know I think
this is a first step to getting there
but we've got to get people into at
least running that just one-week
two-week loop will be that we great
right
the second thing though the keep in mind
is that we have to it's not just about
journalism and the sense making
infrastructure for all of society it's
all about the broken and corrupt
institutions right and you see this a
little bit with the Trump versus the
World Health Organization bit right and
I'm generally I'll have you follow me on
Twitter I'm not the world's biggest fan
of Donald Trump I'm pretty far down the
ladder there but I think he's absolutely
right to go after the World Health
Organization because they absolutely
took the corrupt Chinese government at
their word okay even as they were
burning tens of thousands like they were
creating thousands of bodies or tens of
thousands of bodies a week in Wuhan and
they were telling me what else well I
don't know is there human to human
transmission you know like no come on
come on right so this is the sort of
thing that it's right to hold those
accountable for but it shows that and
this is gonna be where you know bringing
the eric weinstein point that that
basically since the 70s or 80s we've had
these hollowed out institutions that
kind of do the theater they engage in
some cafes the theatre of oh well we're
the blah blah blah we're doing these
things and we put out we have this
meeting and we did this this it's like
hold on a second we can't even figure
out you know where this thing came from
you're telling me you can't even tell me
if there's human human transmission what
those rates look like what are you doing
right so the problem is if we want to
put science forward science has got to
clean up its act right and the broken of
corrupt institutions of academia the
funding vehicles I mean like I worked
with National Science Foundation with
DARPA I've worked with many institutions
here
when you really get in there and you see
you go to the backside of the kitchen or
the restaurant you see a kitchen you see
how the sausage is made it's not pretty
right there's there's a you know we talk
about the revolving door of lobbyists
and things like that in Washington but
there's a revolving door of academics
going to these institutions becoming
program managers one hand washing the
other they see their grad students these
other programs they send money over
there there's like there's a whole
general kind of corrupt bureaucracy
whenever you get humans into a certain
state and so if we want to actually do
ten year level decisioning and
sense-making
for things like climate change which I
think we actually have to do science has
got to get better too it's not just
about journalism or fake news
or idiot citizenry who are uneducated is
that the institutions of science
academia are rather corrupt at this
point I'm long answer for a very short
but very good question sorry and just to
plug Pat Ryan did a talk related to that
which is on the YouTube channel I can
send you that that Peter if you're
interested or even you had a similar
question would you like to follow up
with it sure hi amazing I was just on
your Twitter this morning I've got
pretty hard I pretty got I'm pretty hard
down the rabbit hole for sure wondering
about the ability for us to see this see
this event through see the kind of lag
in our ability to make decisions and
apply that to more wicked problems such
as such as climate change where we have
this this increased lag but the other
question I put into the chat was also
about like communities that have modeled
accurate sense-making
like I know that a lot of tech companies
like instituted like remote work very
early on in this process and I know that
you mentioned like the OODA loop so
there's a lot of startups that already
have these like these models kind of in
their in their businesses so it's kind
of wondering about like what communities
and they're kind of psycho technology or
organizational structures have succeeded
in making
good choices and how you think that
might impact the future evolution of
culture okay fun question so you're
absolutely right that the tech companies
seem to have moved a little bit earlier
in fact my my company and the very first
week of March the first Thursday is what
we told everyone work from home for the
rest of the month at least and the part
of that was because we're here in Austin
and South by Southwest was about to
descend upon us the next week and I said
we're just not even I'm not even messing
around right however I would I do think
some there are communities and subgroups
or subcultures that have been doing
better since making or engaged in higher
quality sense-making around this but I
think that we should be careful about
two possible anti-patterns one thing we
don't do is just match against like oh
tech companies right or any kind of
classical no classical standard or easy
taxonomy of people of tribes and of
coherent structures or coherent movement
and sense making structures I think
those uh those will potentially drag in
a lot of additional variables that are
proxies right so for instance if you're
the top a tech company or if you're in
one of these tech companies they're
organizations tend to be little bit
flatter they can be connected to VCS
which are broad dissemination nexuses
for billionaires and other people who
are truly truly in the know on secret
stuff right so there's just almost like
it's an unfair competition a little bit
because they're closer access to the
edge of whatever is known globally so by
that structure so not like they do
better you know loops in fact they're
little loops may be piss-poor there may
be a lot more tribal groupthink there
but they just have me closer to the
upstream so I want to make sure we don't
inadvertently alias along those kinds of
boundaries and what I would say is that
if I were to run a real program to
analyze to look at what are the
communities that did good work and I
think the verdict is is also too early
to tell right jury still out of who did
a good job or didn't but I would be
generally biasing towards looking for
emergent patterns of communication and
connection as the topology from which I
would then cluster in group
people not on any other kind of I mean I
would not label them by their physical
location and by their place of work and
things like that because those are
strong Network affiliation kind of
factors but I will try to go to a
broader higher dimensional graph to look
at how we cluster cohorts now once we've
done the cohort analysis completely
naive kind of cohort analysis see who's
actually close to who um once we've done
that I think the thing I would be
looking for then did you know mug
analysis I would do within each cohort
is is actually on you use a good word
like the psycho technology it would be
on the basis of the people themselves
and what those people are like and what
their ways of relating to each other is
like because I fundamentally I think in
the game you see this kind of in a lot
of the game be sort of stuff is that we
we really tried to think about the human
connection and the human connection is
the architecture right the human
connection graph and the human
relational capabilities that is the
capability and and the best sense making
around this stuff is not through reading
the it's not like I read and subscribe
to higher funded institutions
institutional sense making things like
there's a $10,000 a month subscription
to some like secret ooh BRR like you
know best info in the world site or
something like that that's not how this
works it's cuz I'm connect to certain
people who I trust very very deeply and
they are connect to other people who
they also trust and hold in high regard
and we in fact have a little bit of
firewalls between each other so when I
get something that's a little bit weird
I'm gonna check it out before I send it
to other people and this looks very very
much like a brain neuronal graph it's
not rocket science it's just it's
neuroscience I guess right it's just
about having high trusted connections
it's about having a human network and no
technology so plants the human network
right so I think there's a deep thing I
would be looking at there is that I
would be looking for I'll be looking for
one you know figure out a way to create
that large high dimensionality cohort
analysis and then within each cohort
doing the genomic analysis of their by
genomic I mean their patterns of
interaction how do the individuals their
you know think and rate rate to each
other cool
Amy you had a question so I I live in
New York and I've been kind of struck by
two different types I felt like people
who are taking this seriously in the
beginning and now I think that they are
very much like masks we have to wear
masks and not save us all and there's
something that is very untethered to the
idea of an autonomous choice and yet
there's also something that's very
tethered to the idea of choice being
almost subconscious or subliminal where
it's like there's this there's this
thing that undergirds people's choice
making that kind of I don't I don't find
it very very conscious on a lot of
people's parts on because people bill
don't social distance even though very
free they went out here so I'm wondering
about like the social consequences of
making unpopular choices and whether or
not you're you're kind of vectoring
toward a a modality of sovereignty and
to hell with photons or maybe social
consequences aren't as important as
individual choice making
yeah yeah I think I see I would take a
couple multiple approaches to your
question there and your observations
there's a there's a term that my physics
mentor back in the day used to say it
was like he would always use terms like
this this problem or this particular
exercise whatever separates the men from
the sheep right it's sort of phrase and
I think this particular consequential
decision it's separating the men from
the sheep all right there's people who
are going to look to the herd and be
like well what okay what's everyone it
was a mask oh I got me put a mask
on right why did I put a mask on I don't
know right like everyone's buying
organic I'm gonna buy organic - wait
what does a Ganic mean you know Oh
everyone's done blah blah I'm gonna do
what without you know that modality of
sheeple and I hate to just like amplify
just a cheap right-wing
[Music]
you know soundbite kind of things but it
really is the appropriate determine in
this case right it is people falling
back into a decision-making mode that is
looking to the herd and and this applies
in all places to like I work in the tech
industry right and in technology you
have the curve of adoption and get
across the chasm and in the lump of
people around the around the standard
around the mean those people make
decisions they make IT buying decisions
technology decisions on the basis of
what everyone in their industry is doing
not on the basis of themselves feeling
like they have the ability to that is
this good or not it's just like well
everyone else in our industry is doing
AI now I guess we gotta go buy some AI
right and so that same thing is just
it's just I think an unfortunate aspect
of where humanity Homo sapiens in sort
of modernity in a technological society
that's just where we're at and it is
primitive and it sucks and I would hope
that my great-grandchildren have
something better but that's just where
we're at right and if you're interested
in this topic if you look at the work of
Simonton or Lowell
ll ul these guys talk a lot about this
kind of thing that as a society gets
more complex there's just a little
taller ladder to climb to even get to a
point where you can have agency and meet
and feel like ok I'm informed enough to
make a real decision about this right I
mean even like with this corner virus
stuff I'm seeing some of these things
around around there being specific parts
of the genome for four places in
particular that correspond to HIV and
these are not point things that would've
been asserted in a rant it seems like it
success it's exceptionally unlikely that
this randomly naturally occurred so
there is now starting to become signal
that from a couple drew places that I'm
seeing that there was actual genomic
engineering that inserted things into
the genome here and there's legitimate
reasons for not for bioweapons research
but for actual vaccine research why you
would do this ok so but I'm not a
geneticist right I mean I can you know
my software is used in genomics I'm how
did you know this myself so I've got to
take that and send off to cup my friends
who are knowledgeable about this sort of
thing so that's what I mean that the
tower of
modernity is so tall most people can't
get up there most people can barely do
like high school algebra so they're
going to fall back to tribal sense
making systems like what is everyone
else doing I don't do what they do so
it's not necessarily an intrinsic like
complete failure
to say oh you guys are just doing tribal
sense making to hell with your troubles
let's make it I'm gonna figure us out of
my own you know a lot of cases you can't
figure it out on you you need to have
the data right there's spy satellites
I've been looking at IR signatures in in
Wuhan and all these other places and
those spy satellites the people
operating them have a lot more
information than you do so this is the
kind of thing that I think it's um it's
hard to make a blanket statement right
that that going and forging on your own
is is is the right thing but certainly
we should what you should do this is the
one thing that I will say you should
connect to other people who are not
afraid to be iconoclastic we're not
afraid to venture far away from the herd
because they know when they come back
the herd will still welcome them and
this is the topic of it's a deep topic
I've not actually done any podcasts on
it or any writing on it outside of a few
Facebook posts but it is the core
struggle of human civilization is how do
we create a tribe mentality and a tribal
coherence mechanism that also treats
outcasts with respect when they return
as genius basically how do we create
greater discernment at an institutional
level between geniuses and assholes how
do you hold liminal door open so we can
say yeah yeah that person is blowing a
lot of stuff up and they're doing weird
things but oh look all of a sudden they
built a rocket and now we have
satellites right or oh that person do
all these terrible things holy crap
they're gonna kill us all we need like
kill them right now right you have to
have this like long period of
discernment as an institution most of
our institutions ground that window to
nothing right if you if you step off
outside of the norms you're done there's
no such thing as shaman and so the idea
that we allow a place for shaman to come
back and lead us to the neck across the
adaptive Ally because you hear in-game
be people talk about the adaptive Ally a
lot the weird idiot that takes the tribe
across adaptive Ally looks like a weird
idiot until they come back with all
these goods from the other side right so
how do we hold open that that
discernment and so I think in your
hits upon that in in a very interesting
way because what you want to do is find
other friends find groups of people that
will support you as you go off and do
weird things right and who if they all
start putting masks on or not to point
if they all start blending Victory
Gardens you should probably start
planning a Victory Garden to or move to
some place we have land and freshwater
to plant Victory Garden right that's the
kind of thing find a better tribe and in
this way we're diffusing the Darwinian
selection process of old broken
institutional structures and yes there's
will be bloodshed and yes people will
die there's a great quote from a book by
Iain Banks called the algebra where one
of the character says to the other in
the best of times the wheels of history
are indifferent to blood and to the
blood of the common man and the guy says
in the best of times
he says and the worst of times they're
lubricated by it you know that's and
that I think is one of these things that
we should all hold in our hearts right
now because we are going through a real
real real crisis right now and the
bloodshed has even begun
you know the bloodbath that's gonna
happen when the economy starts again and
everyone's out of lockdown we realize
centuries-long brand names or had just
evaporate into bankruptcy there's no
there's bad stuff that's gonna happen so
I think right now especially in New York
find find out our friends find a
different group of people that you trust
with a higher to do higher fidelity
that's making great Rob Hudson you had a
question about infinite games yeah the
question I've got on it was very early
on in the conversation I think you evoke
to me this the understanding around game
theory and and finite games use the
prisoner's dilemma so I knew there made
reference to lots lots of different
finite games where it's who gets to
college or mmm-hmm who gets the girl or
whatever it is all of that sort of stuff
is fundamentally finite game and what I
I suspect that were less we are
consciously driven by finite games but
potentially propositional is that we
would ruin by infinite game the infinite
game which is a lot less
conscious its sub minimal as many people
have talked about and what I'm saying is
the crisis is naturally allowing that
deeper agency of wanting and needing to
play the infinite game of cooperation a
win-win cooperative games is starting to
emerge so that was one question really
is that I mean it's very interesting
that we think we live in our heads and
it's the conscious mind but it's it's
it's a peanut in comparison with what's
really going on underneath so we have no
choice from that point of view what's
your thoughts on that that's that's
really that's a really interesting
observation because I think there's my
thing you're talking about meaning was
really tied to this concept there is an
infinite amount of meaning to be had
right it's sort of almost it's it's sort
of like ties to Thomas Jefferson's thing
about if I light your mind with you know
the you know by light your candle if
mine doesn't diminish my flame right the
the kinds you know the really sad and
tragic thing is that if we can get
everyone if we uplevel everyone to a
heart space and a head space where
they're solving for sufficiency and then
you realize there's better modes of
interaction to yield more and more
better things for everyone but if we
create institutions infrastructures from
from from ontological and metaphysical
infrastructures to you know actual
physical infrastructures if we create
these things that reinforce a finite
game competition then we make
as if decision-making we make that feel
consequential when really everyone's
just fighting for scraps and so I I so I
agree with you that there is the the the
infinite game that we should try to get
everyone to play there's an opportunity
for that and it's rooted in meaning and
meaningful decision-making and deep
human relationships things like that and
there's an infinite amount of that to go
around right there's actually have an
embarrassment of riches and and I first
had you know I personally I just as a
personal side note I had that experience
back in like 94 when I first got on
Usenet and I was like
so much like what from BBS culture to
using that and there's a lot more Usenet
than there was just a few BBS forums
right and I was like oh my god I could
just spend the rest of my life
connecting with people and talking to
people and learning from them and all
these things and that sense now how many
websites are there there's like 10 right
we went from like an infinity of Usenet
okay a lot of it was weird trash but
still went from that to like oh everyone
visits the same 10 web sites right and
and so there's this thing where if we
don't up level the human organism if we
don't create infrastructures by
infrastructures I mean societies like
this efforts like this you know things
like this that help people to uplevel
then we can be given the best
infrastructure technology and tools and
we will still create crappy finite games
out of them it's interesting you
mentioned college is one of those things
College should be a place well can you
imagine the privilege of having a place
where you just be fed and just read
books right just talk to people who are
smarter than you with wonderful
equipment to do amazing experiments you
could just do that like wow that's
amazing
but we turned it into a shitty finite
game of credential certification like
that's that's complete crap right so
even given all of these things given the
multi billions of dollars that I'm you
know plunk down into college campuses
and everything in these buildings we
still can't seem to get even in those
most intellectual places this flip over
into let's play an infinite game here
right let's solve for how many students
we can educate to a minimum level every
year and have that be the race versus
how many Nobel Prize winners we have in
our faculty why does someone race that
way right how many you'll have the most
extension education programs and oh by
the way Harvard and stuff building
another 500 million dollar building
somewhere in Massachusetts you can go
and literally educate and feed 20
villages somewhere in some third-world
country like that would be much better
that would literally be much better but
it wouldn't get you the credentials and
wouldn't get you the Flair right so my
point in all of this is that the
opportunity to live meaningful lives to
build societies that encourage people to
live meaningful and abundant lives is
all there that's why I think the game be
sort of proto be movement is starting to
pick up schemes scheme because people
realize
we could do this right this is the thing
we need to do because we could just keep
running down the game a paths of
creating bigger and bigger and more and
more and worse of worse finite games but
the other thing I'll say is that the
game a thing and the finite games this
actually does segue into the second
thing I was gonna talk about the phase
two of what I was talked about which was
Moloch and so on slay star codex is a
brilliant exposition Scott Alexander
about meditations of Moloch and it
really is just as a reflection of the
way the reason why things are the way
they are is because we keep making them
the way they are and Brett Weinstein
talks about this as a David and Goliath
thing I have a medium blog post called
why do I capitalize the E in
establishment and this is you know two
and half years ago
why capitalize the E in establishment
because I was talking about being
anti-establishment and the idea here is
that the system and the game of the
world is actually just a game and this
the other really interesting thing about
Colonel Myers if everyone actually steps
back and pauses and has to make
intentional consequential decisions well
you start from a from a point of
sufficiency do I have food water
utilities are my children safe or my
parents safe like that's where you start
with and then you like well what do I
need beyond that and now so basically
it's like if you switch from one mode to
another then if everyone switches the
other mode there's no need for the
previous mode it's not like there's men
and back rooms like doing like this I
mean like oh we'll pull these levers and
like reprogram ever with five G that's
not how it works right when we have
emergent structures that are
self-sustaining attractors as we call
them right in mathematics and dynamical
systems it's like if you if you ever
seen like a dust devil kind of swirling
across the desert at some point it runs
out of steam it evaporates inside wanted
to go the air is all still there the
dust particles also there they're kind
of floating down it's all still there
but it just is a different configuration
right and so what happens if you have
the stigma jeddak you know you seem the
what they called the murmuration right
all these birds swarming in flying in
formation and stuff and every bird is
making local decision well to the other
birds and when you net that out it
becomes this irrigation that's swarms
and has almost an organic life to itself
but if you could
freeze a blind Abby bird for like two
seconds it was just boom instantly
evaporate right because they would all
make different or you've seen those
things when a big gust of wind comes if
it comes from the same direction it hits
all of them the whole thing actually
responds like a sail
it's just absolutely fascinating watch
these things human civilization is the
same thing right and so to to rise point
about like climate change look we just
totally solved climate change
people just don't travel anymore all
right you see like that now and there's
a say in India they can all the sudden
see the Hemel ayahs again for the first
time in decades right so when you have
like we can all just be like wait a
second do I really have to go that
business trip I didn't I was still able
conduct business right so there's a
there's a thing that the system of the
world Moloch it continues because we
keep doing it and all it takes and what
we've learned with coronavirus this is
the the really interesting generalized
point to take away from it is that a
sufficiently large crisis of some
duration a consequential choice imposed
on everyone with a lag or a gap of a
certain amount of time more than a day
but probably less than a year you know
two weeks seems to be enough with that
you can burp you can hiccup you can
evaporate Moloch that is for me and like
just a few minutes left but for me
that's the interesting thing about the
consequential gap it presents limb
analogy to everyone and all the sudden
boom right so game be I've never felt
better about the prospects for game B
I've never felt better about the
possibility of us actually being able to
within my lifetime make significant
fundamental change with regard to
sustainability and putting humans back
in that sustainable development zone
because it's clear that it's clear that
everyone now has had a moment it's like
a glitch in the matrix but everyone
glitched it once and you realize wait it
was just me dreaming that I was in this
little pod suspended up with some robots
around me we all saw that right like
that is amazing so yes all right
we have will pause there and I just felt
great excitement hearing you say that
Peter I like a yeah energy so yeah
one thing I like about you is just
listening to you and talking with you if
there's like a like many different tree
branches of conversations and questions
just arise so I'd love to have you back
at the the stoah for another session
like this - yeah
and so I'll make some closing thoughts
in a moment but do you have any closing
thoughts uh yourself know I've been
doing a lot of talking I just want to
thank you for for doing this and for
hosting me and having me here I would
thank everyone for for coming here and
giving me your attention and also having
such wonderful comments here and seeing
the chat okay thank you all cool
thanks so much my friend for coming out
today thanks everyone for the excellent
questions the next two events coming up
today we have Yancey Strickler the the
co-founder of Kickstarter he's coming
I think it's let me just get the time he
has 7:00 p.m. Eastern Time it's self
awareness in a crisis he's gonna do a
workshop on his mentalism we have like
about 100 people RSVP for that it would
be quite interesting so we're going to
manage it and followed he's the warm-up
act to calm or existential dance party
that's happening at 8:30 p.m. and I
fully expected Peter willing to be there
so we can get that answer is on
so you just RSVP on the website okay and
the store right now is based off the
gift economy I'm viewing it as a gift
for all of us to freely use in this time
of need if you're inspired to give a
gift to the stoah just go to the website
and look at the gift economy at the
bottom of the page for more information
all right so thanks everyone for coming
up today thank you everyone